I want you to touch your face.
أود منكم أن تلمسوا وجوهكم.
Go on.
استمرو.
What do you feel?
بماذا تشعرون؟
Soft? Squishy?
ناعم؟ طري؟
It's you, right? You're feeling you?
هذا انت، صحيح؟ انت تشعر بنفسك؟
Well, it's not quite true.
حسنا، هذا ليس صحيح كلياً.
You're actually feeling thousands of microscopic creatures
انت في الحقيقه تشعر بالآف المخلوقات المجهرية
that live on our face and fingers.
التي تعيش على وجوهنا واصابعنا.
You're feeling some of the fungi
انت تشعر ببعض الفطريات
that drifted down from the air ducts today.
التي انحرفت إلى الاسفل عبر القنوات الهوائية اليوم.
They set off our allergies
التي تطلق الحساسية لدينا
and smell of mildew.
ورائحة العفن.
You're feeling some of the 100 billion bacterial cells
انت تشعر ببعض من 100 مليار خلية بكتيرية
that live on our skin.
التي تعيش على بشرتك.
They've been munching away at your skin oils and replicating,
وتقوم بالمضغ في زيوت الجلد الخاصة بك وتتكاثر،
producing the smells of body odor.
منتجة روائح الجسد.
You're likely even touching the fecal bacteria
من المرجح أنك تقوم بلمس البكتيريا البرازية
that sprayed onto you the last time you flushed a toilet,
التي رُشت عليك في اخر مرة استخدمت دورة المياه،
or those bacteria that live in our water pipes
او تلك البكتيريا التي تعيش في أنابيب المياه لدينا
and sprayed onto you with your last shower.
ورُشت عليك في اخر مرة قمت فيها بالإستحمام.
Sorry.
اعتذر.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
You're probably even giving a microscopic high five
انك على الأغلب تعطي كفك مجهرياً
to the two species of mites that live on our faces,
لنوعي العث التي تعيش على وجوهنا،
on all of our faces.
على وجوهنا جميعاً.
They've spent the night squirming across your face
لقد امضو الليل يتلون عبر وجهك
and having sex on the bridge of your nose.
ويمارسون العلاقة الزوجية على الجسر الخاص بانفك.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Many of them are now leaking their gut contents onto your pores.
العديد منها تُسرب محتويات أمعائها عبر المسام الخاصة بك.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Now look at your finger.
الان انظر إلى اصبعك.
How's it feel? Gross?
ماهو شعورك؟ مقرف؟
In desperate need of soap or bleach?
في حاجة ماسة للصابون والمبيض؟
That's how you feel now,
هذا ماتشعر به الان،
but it's not going to be how you feel in the future.
ولكنه ليس ما ستشعر به في المستقبل.
For the last 100 years,
في ال100 سنة الأخيرة،
we've had an adversarial relationship
كانت لدينا علاقة خصومة
with the microscopic life nearest us.
مع الحياة المجهرية القريبة منا.
If I told you there was a bug in your house
لو قمت بإخبارك أن هناك حشرة في منزلك
or bacteria in your sink,
او بكتيريا في المغسلة،
there was a human-devised solution for that,
كان هناك حل انساني مبدع لهذه المشكلة،
a product to eradicate, exterminate,
منتجات للإستئصال، الإبادة،
disinfect.
تعقيم.
We strive to remove most of the microscopic life in our world now.
ونحن نسعى جاهدين لإزالة معظم الحياة المجهرية في عالمنا الآن.
But in doing so, we're ignoring the best source of new technology
ولكن خلال سعينا لذلك، نحن نتجاهل افضل مصدر للطاقة الجديدة
on this planet.
على هذا الكوكب.
The last 100 years have featured human solutions to microbial problems,
في الـ100 سنة الأخيرة ظهرت حلول انسانية للمشاكل الميكروبية،
but the next 100 years will feature microbial solutions to human problems.
ولكن خلال الـ100 سنة القادمة ستظهر حلول ميكروبية للمشاكل الإنسانية.
I'm a scientist, and I work with researchers
انا عالمة، وأعمل مع الباحثين
at North Carolina State University and the University of Colorado
في جامعة ولاية كارولينا الشمالية وجامعة كولورادو
to uncover the microscopic life that is nearest us,
للكشف عن الحياة المجهرية الأقرب لنا،
and that's often in our most intimate and boring environments,
وغالبا مايكون ذلك في بيئتنا الأكثر حميمة ومللاً،
be it under our couches, in our backyards,
سواء كان ذلك تحت الأرائك او في فنائنا الخلفي،
or in our belly buttons.
او في الصرة الخاصة بنا.
I do this work because it turns out that we know very little
انا اقوم بهذا العمل لانه اتضح اننا نعرف القليل جدا
about the microscopic life that's nearest us.
عن الحياة المجهرية الاقرب الينا.
As of a few years ago, no scientist could tell you
منذ بضع سنوات مضت لم يتمكن أي عالم من اخباركم
what bugs or microorganisms live in your home --
ان الحشرات والكائنات المجهرية التي تعيش في منزلك--
your home, the place you know better than anywhere else.
منزلك، المكان الذي تعرفه أكثر من أي مكان اخر.
And so I and teams of others
وهكذا أنا وفريق من العلماء الاخرين
are armed with Q-tips and tweezers
مسلحين بأعواد القطن والملاقط
and advanced DNA techniques
وتقنيات الحمض النووي المتطورة
to uncover the microscopic life nearest us.
للكشف عن الحياة المجهرية الأقرب منا.
In doing so, we found over 600 species of bugs
خلال قيامنا بذلك، وجدنا اكثر من 600
that live in USA homes,
فصيلة من الحشرات تعيش في منازل أمريكا،
everything from spiders and cockroaches
جميع الأنواع من العناكب و الصراصير
to tiny mites that cling to feathers.
إلى أنواع العث الصغيرة التي تتشبث بالريش.
And we found over 100,000 species of bacteria and fungi
ووجدنا أكثر من100,000 فصيلة من البكتيريا
that live in our dust bunnies,
والفطريات التي تعيش في ادوات تنضيف الغبار،
thousands more that live on our clothes or in our showers.
والآلاف ايضاً تعيش على ملابسنا وفي أماكن الإستحمام.
We've gone further still,
ولقد ذهبنا إلى أبعد من ذلك،
and we looked at the microorganisms
ونظرنا إلى الكائنات المجهرية
that live inside the bodies of each of those bugs in our home.
التي تعيش داخل أجساد الحشرات التي تعيش في منازلنا.
In each bug, for example, a wasp,
في كل حشرة، مثلا، دبور،
we see a microscopic jungle unfold in a petri plate,
لقد رأينا غابة مجهرية في اللوحات المخبرية،
a world of hundreds of vibrant species.
عالم من مئات الأنواع النابضة بالحياة.
Behold the biological cosmos!
نظام بيولوجي متكامل!
So many of the species you're looking at right now
الكثيرمن الفصائل التي تنظرون لها الآن
don't yet have names.
ليس لديها أسماء حتى الآن.
Most of the life around us remains unknown.
أغلب الأشياء الحية من حولنا لاتزال غير معروفة.
I remember the first time I discovered and got to name a new species.
أتذكر المرة الأولى التي اكتشفت فصيلة جديدة وتمكنت من تسميتها.
It was a fungus that lives in the nest of a paper wasp.
كانت نوع من الفطريات التي تعيش في عُش دبور الورق.
It's white and fluffy,
كانت بيضاء وبها زغب،
and I named it "mucor nidicola,"
وقد اسميتها "موكور نيديكولا"
meaning in Latin that it lives in the nest of another.
ومعنى ذلك بالاتينية أنها تعيش في عُش الغير.
This is a picture of it growing on a dinosaur,
هذه صورة لها وهي تتحول إلى ديناصور،
because everyone thinks dinosaurs are cool.
لأن الجميع يعتقد أن الديناصورات رائعة.
At the time, I was in graduate school,
في ذلك الوقت، كنت اقوم بالدراسات العليا،
and I was so excited that I had found this new life form.
وكنت في غاية الحماس لأنني وجدت شكل الحياة الجديد هذا.
I called up my dad, and I go,
اتصلت بوالدي، وقلت له،
"Dad! I just discovered a new microorganism species."
"أبي! لقد اكتشفت فصيلة جديدة من الكائنات المجهرية."
And he laughed and he goes,
ضحك وقال,
"That's great. I hope you also discovered a cure for it."
"ذلك رائع. ارجو ايضاً أن تكتشفي علاج لذلك."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
"Cure it."
"علاج لذلك."
Now, my dad is my biggest fan,
الآن، والدي هو اكثر الناس اعجاباً بي،
so in that crushing moment where he wanted to kill my new little life form,
في تلك اللحظة الساحقة حينما أراد قتل شكل الحياة الجديد الذي قمت بإكتشافه،
I realized that actually I had failed him,
ادركت أنني خيبت أمله،
both as a daughter and a scientist.
فشلت كإبنة له و كعالمة.
In my years toiling away in labs and in people's backyards,
في سنواتي التي كدحت بها في المعامل والأفنية الخلفية للناس،
investigating and cataloging the microscopic life around us,
أقوم بالتحقيق والفهرسة للحياة المجهرية من حولنا،
I'd never made clear my true mission to him.
لم أقم أبدا باِيضاح مهمتي الحقيقية له.
My goal is not to find technology
لم يكن هدفي إيجاد تكنولوجيا
to kill the new microscopic life around us.
لقتل الحياة المجهرية الجديدة من حولنا.
My goal is to find new technology from this life, that will help save us.
هدفي هو إيجاد تكنولوجيا جديدة من هذه الحياة، تساعد على انقاذنا.
The diversity of life in our homes is more than a list of 100,000 new species.
أنواع الحياة في منازلنا هي أكبر من قائمة تضم 100,000 فصيلة جديدة.
It is 100,000 new sources of solutions to human problems.
إنها 100,000مصدر كحلول للمشاكل الإنسانية.
I know it's hard to believe that anything that's so small
اعلم أن ذلك أمر صعب تصديقة أن شيئ بهذا الصغر
or only has one cell
او يحوي خلية واحده فقط
can do anything powerful,
يمكنه عمل شيء بمنتهى القوة،
but they can.
ولكنهم يستطيعون.
These creatures are microscopic alchemists,
هذه الكائنات هي الكيميائيون المجهريون،
with the ability to transform their environment
مع القدرة على تحويل بيئتهم
with an arsenal of chemical tools.
مع ترسانة من الأدوات الكيميائية.
This means that they can live anywhere on this planet,
هذا يعني أنه لديهم القدرة على العيش في أي مكان على هذه الكوكب،
and they can eat whatever food is around them.
ويمكنهم أكل أي نوع من الغذاء حولهم.
This means they can eat everything from toxic waste to plastic,
وهذا يعني أنهم يستطيعون أكل كل شيء من النفايات السامة إلى البلاستيك،
and they can produce waste products like oil and battery power
ويستطيعون إنتاج نفايات مثل الزيت والطاقة
and even tiny nuggets of real gold.
وحتى شذرات صغيرة من الذهب الحقيقي.
They can transform the inedible into nutritive.
يستطيعون تحويل المواد الغير قابلة للأكل إلى مواد مغذية.
They can make sugar into alcohol.
بإمكانهم تحويل السكر إلى الكحول.
They give chocolate its flavor,
يقومون بإعطاء الشوكلاته نكهتها،
and soil the power to grow.
والتربة القدرة على النمو.
I'm here to tell you
أنا هنا لأقول لكم
that the next 100 years will feature these microscopic creatures
أن الـ100 سنة المقبلة ستعرض هذه الكائنات المجهرية
solving more of our problems.
وهي تقوم بحل المزيد من مشاكلنا.
And we have a lot of problems to choose from.
ولدينا الكثير من المشاكل لنختار منها.
We've got the mundane: bad-smelling clothes or bland food.
لدينا المشاكل الإعتيادية: الملابس ذات الرائحة الكريهة او الطعام السئ
And we've got the monumental:
ولدينا المشاكل الضخمة:
disease, pollution, war.
المرض، التلوث، الحرب.
And so this is my mission:
وعليه هذه هي مهمتي:
to not just catalog the microscopic life around us,
ليس فقط فهرسة الحياة المجهرية من حولنا،
but to find out what it's uniquely well-suited to help us with.
ولكن لمعرفة ماهي مميزاتها المناسبة لمساعدتنا.
Here's an example.
إليكم مثال.
We started with a pest,
لقد بدأنا مع الافات،
a wasp that lives on many of our homes.
دبور يعيش في العديد من مازلنا.
Inside that wasp, we plucked out a little-known microorganism species
بداخل الدبور، وجدنا فصيلة مجهرية معروفة
with a unique ability:
مع قدرة مميزة:
it could make beer.
القدرة على صناعة البيره.
This is a trait that only a few species on this planet have.
هذه مَيزة عدد قليل من الفصائل تمتلكها على كوكبنا.
In fact, all commercially produced beer you've ever had
الحقيقة،كل منتجات البيره التجارية لدينا
likely came from one of only three microorganism species.
على الأغلب انها من مصدر واحد فقط من ثلاثة فصائل مجهرية.
Yet our species, it could make a beer that tasted like honey,
ولكن هذه الفصيلة، تستطيع صنع بيره لها مذاق العسل،
and it could also make a delightfully tart beer.
ويمكنها أيضا أن تجعل البيره ذات مذاق رائع ولاذع.
In fact, this microorganism species that lives in the belly of a wasp,
الحقيقة، هذه الفصيلة المجهرية الدقيقة التي تعيش في بطن الدبور،
it could make a valuable sour beer
تستطيع صنع بيره قيمة وحامضة
better than any other species on this planet.
أفضل من أي فصيلة أخرى على هذا الكوكب.
There are now four species that produce commercial beer.
يوجد الآن أربع فصائل تنتج البيرة التجارية.
Where you used to see a pest,
حيث كنت ترى استخدام الافات،
now think of tasting your future favorite beer.
الآن فكر في تذوق بيرتك المستقبلية المفضلة.
As a second example,
كمثال ثاني،
I worked with researchers to dig in the dirt in people's backyards.
عملت مع الباحثين للحفر في أفنية الناس القذرة.
There, we uncovered a microorganism that could make novel antibiotics,
هناك، اكتشفنا كائنات مجهرية دقيقة بامكانها صنع مضادات حيوية جديدة،
antibiotics that can kill the world's worst superbugs.
مضادات حيوية تستطيع قتل اسوأ الجراثيم في العالم.
This was an awesome thing to find,
كان ذلك إكتشاف رائع،
but here's the secret:
ولكن هذا هو السر:
for the last 60 years,
خلال الـ60 سنة الأخيرة،
most of the antibiotics on the market
معظم المضادات الحيوية في السوق
have come from similar soil bacteria.
تأتي من بكتيريا مماثلة لبكتيريا التربة.
Every day, you and I and everyone in this room
كل يوم، أنت وأنا والجميع في هذه الغرفة
and on this planet,
وفي هذا الكوكب،
are saved by similar soil bacteria that produce most of our antibiotics.
يتم انقاذهم ببكتيريا مشابهة لبكتيريا التربة التي تُنتج أغلب مضاداتنا الحيوية.
Where you used to see dirt,
حين كنت ترى التربة على أنها أوساخ،
now think of medication.
الآن فكر في الدواء.
Perhaps my favorite example comes from colleagues
ربما مثالي المفضل يأتي من الزملاء الذين
who are studying a pond scum microorganism,
يدرسون الكائنات المجهرية في روث البقر،
which is tragically named after the cow dung it was first found in.
والتي سميت بشكل مأساوي على إسم روث البقر حيث وُجدت لأول مرة.
It's pretty unremarkable and would be unworthy of discussion,
انها أمر غير مُلاحظ وغير جدير بالمناقشة،
except that the researchers found that if you feed it to mice,
غير أن الباحثون وجدو أنه عند تغذية الفئران بها،
it vaccinates against PTSD.
فإنه يحصنها من اضطراب مابعد الصدمة.
It vaccinates against fear.
يحصنها من الخوف.
Where you used to see pond scum, now think of hope.
حينما ترى الآن روث البقر فكر في الأمل.
There are so many more microbial examples
هناك الكثير من الأمثلة للكائنات المجهرية
that I don't have time to talk about today.
التي لايسعني الوقت للتحدث عنها اليوم.
I gave you examples of solutions that came from just three species,
لقد اعطيتكم أمثلة لحلول تأتي من ثلاث فصائل فقط،
but imagine what those other 100,000 species in your dust bunnies
ولكم أن تتخيلو الـ100,000 الفصيلة الأخرى التي تعيش في أداة تنضيف الغبار
might be able to do.
وما قد تستطيع فعله.
In the future, they might be able to make you sexier
في المستقبل، قد تستطيع جعلك أكثر جاذبية
or smarter
أو ذكاءً
or perhaps live longer.
أو ربما تمنحك حياة أطول.
So I want you to look at your finger again.
لذلك أُريدكم أن تنظرو إلى إصبعكم مجدداً.
Think about all those microscopic creatures
فكرو في كل هذه الكائنات المجهرية
that are unknown.
الغير معروفة.
Think about in the future what they might be able to do
فكرو في المستقبل ما قد تكون قادرة على القيام به
or make
او ما ستصنعه
or whose life they might be able to save.
او حياة الأشخاص التي ستتمكن من انقاذها.
How does your finger feel right now?
كيف ستشعر بإصبعك الآن؟
A little bit powerful?
قوي بعض الشيء؟
That's because you're feeling the future.
ذلك لأنك تشعر بالمستقبل.
Thank you.
شكراً لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)